<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Enemy Territory on sagan.onroids.com</title>
    <link>https://sagan.onroids.com/tags/enemy-territory/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Enemy Territory on sagan.onroids.com</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 30 Aug 2016 11:08:15 -0600</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://sagan.onroids.com/tags/enemy-territory/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Sagan on DB: Ode to ET</title>
      <link>https://sagan.onroids.com/sagan-on-db-ode-to-et</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Aug 2016 11:08:15 -0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sagan.onroids.com/sagan-on-db-ode-to-et</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Hello all and welcome to the first post in a series I&amp;rsquo;m calling &lt;a href=&#34;http://asdf.com&#34;&gt;Sagan on DB&lt;/a&gt;,
where I&amp;rsquo;ll be writing about my thoughts and ideas about &lt;a href=&#34;http://dirtybomb.nexon.net/&#34;&gt;Dirty Bomb&lt;/a&gt;. I plan to
cover various facets of the game, from reviving competitive, to map design,
monetization, loadouts, crafting, and polish. In this post I&amp;rsquo;ll talk about why
I still play Dirty Bomb, and what DB can learn from Enemy Territory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dirty Bomb is one of the best, most underrated FPS games available today.
Heavily influenced by Splash Damage&amp;rsquo;s 2003 &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.splashdamage.com/wolfet&#34;&gt;Wolfenstein: Enemy Territory&lt;/a&gt;,
Dirty Bomb is a rare combination of fast, skillful gunplay and smooth movement,
with team-based spawn waves and map-specific objectives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unlike some other popular FPS games, every class in Dirty Bomb can be combat
effective, and they all have moderately high skill ceilings. The classes
are well balanced. There&amp;rsquo;s no overpowered abilities or stuns (other
than Thunder). It&amp;rsquo;s not unusual to see support classes
out-fragging Fraggers. Ultimately, if you have good game-sense
and can land those crucial headshots, you will be effective no matter what class
you are.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This makes learning Dirty Bomb tough. Most people won&amp;rsquo;t be able to install and
instantly be good. In fact they&amp;rsquo;ll probably get demolished by veterans and
promptly uninstall. Just like anything else, you have to practice to get
better. But if you have the willpower to push through and learn from your
mistakes, mastering a class in Dirty Bomb is one of the most satisfying feelings
I&amp;rsquo;ve had in FPS gaming.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The skill ceiling also makes high-level competitive play really exciting to
watch. I can still remember some of the early Dirty Cups tournament matches
between v586 (pkD), SICK6, zfz, BzNs, and others. It was early days, and teams
were still figuring out the competitive meta, but even then there were some
incredibly exciting moments. Last second defuses, insane snipes, clutch plays,
it was all there. It&amp;rsquo;s one of the best games to watch at a competitive level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But Dirty Bomb is far from perfect. The competitive scene used to be very
healthy, with several sponsored teams, prize money tournaments, thousands of
Twitch viewers, and generally lots of excitement for the future. These days,
not so much. Almost all of the teams that used to play in Dirty Cups/&lt;a href=&#34;http://dbnation.net&#34;&gt;DBN&lt;/a&gt;
tournaments have left for other games, and they haven&amp;rsquo;t been replaced. Player
numbers continue to &lt;a href=&#34;https://steamdb.info/app/333930/graphs/&#34;&gt;slowly decline&lt;/a&gt;. There aren&amp;rsquo;t many maps. Almost all of the
maps have balance issues, some more than others (Terminal).
Objective/Stopwatch maps have been left untouched for almost a year now. The
loadout system is universally hated and needs significant changes. Ranked takes
forever to find a match. And then there&amp;rsquo;s the bugs, the slow performance, UI sluggishness, et
cetera, et cetera.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dirty Bomb isn&amp;rsquo;t dead, but it doesn&amp;rsquo;t have the life that it used to. Right now,
it feels like it&amp;rsquo;s in limbo. It still has incredible competitive potential,
but there&amp;rsquo;s no telling if it will ever get there, or if the player numbers will
continue to slowly decline until the game is completely irrelevant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I still believe that Dirty Bomb can be the next Counter-Strike, but it is going
to require Splash Damage to re-evaluate their priorities. To explain what
these priorities should be, let&amp;rsquo;s take a brief look back at what made
Splash Damage&amp;rsquo;s first game such a beloved classic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;wolfenstein-enemy-territory:18acb8724f109415abf4a83a71bc82ec&#34;&gt;Wolfenstein: Enemy Territory&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;(screenshot of ET)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wolfenstein: Enemy Territory (ET) started development as a paid
expansion for &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Id_Software&#34;&gt;id Software&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;RtCW&#34;&gt;Return to Castle Wolfenstein&lt;/a&gt;. Development
was split up between two companies, with Splash Damage being responsible for the
multiplayer. The single-player campaign was never finished, and ET was going to
be scraped, but thankfully id recognized the good hard work by Splash Damage and
decided to release the game as a free, stand-alone title.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Remember, this was in 2003, before free-to-play and micro-transactions were a
thing. This was incredible at the time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All the things that make Dirty Bomb fun today were there in ET back then (and
RtCW before that). It was fast, centered around gunplay, with spawn waves and
objectives. Good simple fun.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As fun as it was, ET wasn&amp;rsquo;t without its problems. There were bugs. Hitboxes were
weird. There were only six maps, some of which had major balance issues. Tools
for competitive play just weren&amp;rsquo;t there. And since no one was making money from
ET, it wasn&amp;rsquo;t looking like any of these issues would ever be fixed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite this, over 13 years later ET lives on today with a &lt;a href=&#34;http://et.trackbase.net/map/2/&#34;&gt;surprisingly
healthy playerbase&lt;/a&gt;. Right now you can install ET with the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.etlegacy.com/&#34;&gt;ET: Legacy&lt;/a&gt;
installer (or the &lt;a href=&#34;https://etui.kashu.fr/&#34;&gt;ET Ultimate Installer&lt;/a&gt; + &lt;a href=&#34;http://etkey.org/pages/punkbuster/auto---install-for-windows-by-harlekin.php&#34;&gt;ETKey installer&lt;/a&gt;), fire up the game,
and have dozens of servers full of players to choose from.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How can a decade-old game with no developers still have a healthy playerbase?
Because early on, Splash Damage released tools for community mods, maps, and
servers. They gave the community the tools to grow organically.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mod makers, like the team behind &lt;a href=&#34;http://etpro.anime.net/&#34;&gt;ETPro&lt;/a&gt;, fixed hitboxes, fixed bugs, added
competitive rulesets, spectator locking, referee commands, new weapons, new
textures, new sounds, and more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Map makers fixed balance issues in Splash Damage&amp;rsquo;s official maps, ported old
RtCW maps, and created hundreds of new maps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, community servers brought mods and maps together to tailor whatever
kind of experience they wanted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some servers focused on competitive. Those
servers would usually run ETPro, have limited slots, friendly-fire on, and run
maps that were in the competitive rotation. If you joined one of these servers
you better be prepared for a challenge because you were going to be playing with
the best.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most of the servers weren&amp;rsquo;t like this though. In fact, the majority of servers
were pretty casual. Most people didn&amp;rsquo;t care about competitive or
being the best, they just wanted to play some games with their friends. These
servers would usually run mods like Jaymod, which added stuff like shotguns,
poison gas, and throwing knives. They&amp;rsquo;d run all kinds of different maps, too.
Baserace, the ultimate casual pub map, was a capture-the-flag style map that had
teams steal crates from the enemy base to upgrade their own. They could chose to
upgrade their walls, create turrets, sniper towers, supply stations, etc. It was
a lot of fun.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then there were the trickjumping servers, which were a completely different
experience from the rest of the game. They would usually run a mod like [TJMod]
that let you save/teleport to a position in the map. This would make practicing
trickjumps a lot easier. Some trickjumping maps were just a compilation of jumps
from competitive maps. Others focused on gamma jumps&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This holy trifecta of community mods, maps, and servers, is what enabled ET to
persevere while other games come and go.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dirty Bomb in its current state reminds me a lot of vanilla ET. It&amp;rsquo;s a fun,
solid shooter, but the maps aren&amp;rsquo;t the best and it&amp;rsquo;s missing a lot of features
for competitive play. It hasn&amp;rsquo;t reached its full potential.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>